

# Megan E. Dolan

2200 NE Westwood Dr.
Pullman, WA 99163
(309) 531-9370
megan.dolan@wsu.edu
www.megandolan.com

#### **OVERVIEW**

I am a dependable, hard-working researcher interested in genomics and computational biology. As both an avid and adaptable learner, I work well both individually and in teams. My current goals include completing a Master's degree in Biology, expanding my computational skill set, and contributing to genomic research.

#### **EDUCATION**

MS Biology 2019-Present

Washington State University
Certificate: Bioinformatics

BS Biology 2015-2019

Illinois Wesleyan University
Minor: Computer Science

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Characterization of *Theobroma cacao* microbiome, Master's Thesis 2019-Present Washington State University, Advisor: Dr. Omar Cornejo

- Quantified relative abundance and relatedness of microorganisms in 200 *T. cacao* samples to characterize microbes across different host populations.
- Identified differential representation of metabolic pathways in microbe genomes.
- For more information, please visit www.megandolan.com/Research.

# Development of Bacteriophage Database, Independent Research Illinois Wesleyan University, Advisor: Dr. David Bollivar

- Created a web-based application that allows students to input data regarding newly discovered bacteriophages into a university database.
- Allows users to edit their information without deleting/changing information regarding other student's discovered bacteriophages.

# Annotation of Potential Helicase Gene, Independent Research Illinois Wesleyan University, Advisor: Dr. David Bollivar

2018

2018

- Conducted analysis of potential ATP-dependent helicase gene in recently discovered bacteriophage "MrWorf" and annotated genomes within host *Rhodobacter capsulatus* bacteriophage cluster for genetic similarity.
- Presented written report summarizing research to biology faculty, staff, and students.

International Rice Research Institute, Advisor: Dr. Mallikarjuna Swamy

- Studied biofortification of high zinc rice varieties in the Plant Breeding Division.
  - Conducted activities related to rice hybridization, element concentration measurements, phenotyping and genotyping, data gathering, analysis, and QTL mapping.
  - Prepared written and oral report summarizing experience and presented among Plant Breeding research team.

#### Faculty Advised Research

2015-2016

Illinois Wesleyan University, Advisors: Dr. Richard Alvey and Dr. David Bollivar

- Worked for the Science Education Alliance Program: Phage Hunters Advancing Genomics and Evolutionary Science (also known as SEA-PHAGES).
- Isolated, purified, sequenced, and analyzed newly discovered bacteriophages.
- Presented relevance research at the John Wesley Powell Research Conference in the spring.

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

#### Mentor for Undergraduate Researcher

Present

Washington State University, Biological Sciences

- Responsible for organizing and instructing undergraduate mentee in contribution to the cacao project.
- Hold biweekly meetings for open discussions regarding research objectives, related journal articles and reviews, troubleshooting concerns, and general professional advice.

# Principles of Organic Evolution (BIOL 405), Teaching Assistant

Present

Washington State University, Biological Sciences

- Taught an average of 25 undergraduate students per section, with one section per semester.
- Taught hour long introduction lectures each week, actively led class discussions, and assisted with answering questions that covered a range of introductory concepts in evolutionary biology.

### Organismal Biology (BIOL 106), Teaching Assistant

2019

Washington State University, **Biological Sciences** 

- Taught an average of 35 undergraduate students per section, with three sections per semester.
- The course covered a range of topics pertaining to plant and animal anatomy/physiology.

#### Plant and Fungal Diversity (BIOL 306), Teaching Assistant

2017-2018

Illinois Wesleyan University, Biological Sciences

- Taught an average of 35 undergraduate students per semester.
- Assisted students with classifying and identifying specimen in taxonomic ordering, such as: fungi, slime molds, cyanobacteria, algae, bryophytes, eusporangiate and leptosporangiate gymnosperms, and angiosperms.

#### Plant Anatomy and Physiology (BIOL 375), Teaching Assistant

2018

Illinois Wesleyan University, Biological Sciences

- Taught an average of 25 undergraduate students per semester
- The course covered the following topics: plant cell structures, vegetative and reproductive plant body structure in angiosperms, pollination syndromes, sporogenesis, gametogenesis, fruit and flower morphologies, and plant tissue types.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 3. **Dolan, M.** and Cornejo, O. (2020) Diverse endophyte composition across highly divergent populations of the chocolate tree, Theobroma cacao L. Manuscript in preparation, School of Biological Sciences, Washington State University.
- 2. **Dolan, M.** (2020) A Web-Based Application for Efficient Organization of Microbial Genomic Data. Manuscript in preparation, Department of Biological Sciences, Illinois Wesleyan University.
- 1. **Dolan, M.** (2020) Web-Based Bacteriophage Organization System. Department of Biological Sciences, Illinois Wesleyan University. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.3625228.

### **PRESENTATIONS**

**Dolan, M.** (2018). Development of a Rhodobacter capsulatus Bacteriophage Database Application. Oral presentation given at the IWU Criley Research Conference.

**Dolan, M.** (2017). Zinc Biofortification Research Conducted at the International Rice Research Institute. Oral presentation given at the IWU Biology Internship Conference.

Braun, M., **Dolan, M.**, Lennon, J. Lane, S., and Alvey, R. (2016). *Genetic Analyses and Annotations of Three Newly Discovered C1 Mycobacteriophages*. Poster session presented at the John Wesley Powell Research Conference.

## GRANTS AND AWARDS TOTAL: \$7,031.46

Carl H. Elling Travel Endowment Washington State University - \$531.46	2019
Criley Research Fellowship Grant Illinois Wesleyan University - \$4,000.00	2018
Freeman Asia Internship Grant Illinois Wesleyan University - \$2,500.00	2017

#### **HONORS**

Undergraduate Dean's List Illinois Wesleyan

2018, 2019

#### COMPUTER SKILLS

Basic Language Comprehension:

HTML, CSS, JavaScript, C++, C, Python, Perl, R, SQL

Basic Database Management Comprehension:

MongoDB, MySQL, SQLite

# **ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE**

#### Greenhouse Assistant Manager

2017-Present

Illinois Wesleyan University, Advisor: Prof. Bethany Evans-Campbell

- Maintained a diverse collection of plant species, including: bryophytes, eusporangiate and leptosporangiate gymnosperms, and angiosperms.
- Attended to daily greenhouse up-keeping.

# **PROFESSIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

Graduate Women's Alliance in Academia	2020-Present
Active Member	
Graduate Women in Science (GWIS)	2020-Present
Active Member	
The National Society of Leadership and Success	2018-Present
Inducted/Active Member	
The National FFA Organization	2013-Present
Student Advisor, Secretary, and Alumni	

# **COMMUNITY SERVICE/ADDITIONAL AFFILIATIONS**

Million Women Mentors (MWM)	2020-Present
Volunteer Mentor	
Palouse Science (Children's) Discovery Center	2019-Present
Volunteer Member	
Alpha Phi Omega – Professional Service Fraternity	2018-Present
Inducted Member	
IWU Peace Garden	2016 - 2019
Community Volunteer Member	